<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>io.github.salvogendut.Emulator1984</id>
  <name>1984</name>
  <summary>Amstrad CPC 464/6128 emulator</summary>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-2.0-only</project_license>
  <developer id="io.github.salvogendut">
    <name>Salvatore Bognanni</name>
  </developer>
  <description>
    <p>
      1984 is a cycle-stepped Amstrad CPC 464/6128 emulator written in C with SDL3.
      The core machine — Z80 CPU, MC6845 CRTC, AY-3-8912 PSG, uPD765 FDC, Gate
      Array, keyboard, joystick/gamepad and cassette tape — runs commercial
      games and standard software at full speed.
    </p>
    <p>Expansion peripherals emulated:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>DS12887 real-time clock (Cyboard / SYMBiFACE II compatible)</li>
      <li>SYMBiFACE II / Cyboard IDE (raw disk images, FAT16/FAT32)</li>
      <li>SYMBiFACE II PS/2 mouse</li>
      <li>Net4CPC W5100S Ethernet</li>
      <li>Albireo USB host (CH376) for UNIDOS and SymbOS</li>
      <li>M4 board (file API + ESP8266-style networking)</li>
    </ul>
  </description>
  <launchable type="desktop-id">io.github.salvogendut.Emulator1984.desktop</launchable>
  <url type="homepage">https://github.com/salvogendut/1984</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/salvogendut/1984/issues</url>
  <content_rating type="oars-1.1" />
  <releases>
    <release version="0.4.11" date="2026-06-28">
      <description>
        <p>Display and audio overhaul. New Real CRT post-process under Advanced — adjustable scanline opacity, brightness, contrast, and per-channel red/green/blue gain for white-point and tint correction (#81, #195). AY-3-8912 output is now interleaved stereo with Caprice32-style ABC channel panning (blendable from mono to full separation), a perceptual master volume control, and a DC blocker that kills the clicks register 7 used to make when toggling a channel mid-frame (#178); the envelope prescaler and sampled-audio playback are corrected so digi-tunes and effects sound right (#179, #186). On-screen toast notifications surface hardware events (USIfAC link-up, client connect/disconnect) in a fading bottom-left "smoked" panel, toggleable between screen / console / off, with a debug-gated stderr echo (#190); the activity LEDs gain hover labels (#191). The MC6845 CRTC gains overscan and hybrid screen-mode support — split-screen via mid-frame R-register reprogramming, R9 character-height changes, rupture-style raster tricks, and a modelled displayed-address pipeline — fixing raster timing in Bomb Jack, Batman Forever, and Xevious (#170, #181, #183, #105). CP/M Plus ROM probe fallback fixed (#108).</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.10" date="2026-06-26">
      <description>
        <p>Overlay polish and small fixes. The Extensions tab is now tighter: "PDF printer" is just "Printer", "Wi-Fi modem (PerryFi)" is now the "Retro Wi-Fi Modem" (PerryFi-inspired), and the Printer mode (PDF / Real printer) selector has moved to Advanced where it belongs (#168). Media overlay shows the full path of the inserted disk image instead of just the basename, remembers the last-used picker directory across all dialogs (disks, snapshots, video capture, printer dir — printer keeps its own dedicated location when set), and binds N on a drive row to create a new blank .dsk via a save-as picker (#173, #107). Windows builds now persist config under %APPDATA%\\1984 so settings survive between launches (#174, #106). USIfAC control-byte handling has been brought in line with the real PIC firmware — empty-sentinel toggle, ring reset, burst on/off, report queries, board-disable are all handled (#172, #171). And the USIfAC PTY/listener is no longer opened when the MX4 expansion bus is off (#175).</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.9" date="2026-06-23">
      <description>
        <p>New Centronics parallel printer (port &amp;EFxx) emulation with a Cairo-backed PDF host sink: PRINT #8 / LIST #8 / CP/M LST: / AMSDOS printer routing all land in timestamped PDFs in a user-picked directory (folder picker on the new Extensions overlay row). A "Real printer" mode spools each finalised page to the host's default CUPS printer via lp, escaping distrobox / flatpak sandboxes via distrobox-host-exec and flatpak-spawn --host so the host's CUPS stack is reachable without installing cups-client in the container. Sink changes take effect immediately. New --printer-pdf=DIR / --printer-real CLI flags. The printer is gated on the MX4 expansion bus; the warm-amber LED in the activity bar mirrors that gate. Cairo is an optional dependency at configure time; --without-cairo falls back to a no-op host sink so the port is still decoded. Stack of two fixes underneath: matched Caprice32's strobe model (emit on every byte with raw bit 7 set) and corrected PPI port B bit 6 (printer BUSY) polarity so the OS firmware printer routine actually proceeds to the write instead of looping. Closes #162 (#163).</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.8" date="2026-06-21">
      <description>
        <p>New Monochrome display tint (off / green / amber / white) under Advanced — emulates a period GT65 green-phosphor monitor (and amber / paper-white variants) by mapping the CPC hardware palette through a Rec. 601 luma transform at ink-resolve time; border tints with the inks (#158). 1984(1) man page shipped and installed under $mandir/man1 (#159). Activity LED bar now has a 1.5× wide 3-segment M4 indicator (power / disk / net) and a documented slot map at docs/LEDS.md (#154, #156). FUZIX over Net4CPC works end-to-end after fixing the W5100S handshake, auto-assigned source port, Sn_IR clear, and chip-wide IR summary (#150); ephemeral port is now randomized per process so reconnects don't loop on challenge-ACK (#153). M4 board implements C_ROMLOW (0x433D) so FUZIX v2.0.7+ detects it (#151). SDCC .map files can now be imported into the F8 monitor with --symbols, including per-bank scoping for FUZIX (#152). New USIfAC II RS232 emulation (closes #36) (#148). Scripted joystick driver + headless capture for automated UI tests (#149). 664 ROMs (OS_664, BASIC_664, AMSDOS_664) are now shipped in the RPM, and `make dist` produces a buildable tarball.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.7" date="2026-06-16">
      <description>
        <p>FUZIX (ajcasado cpcsme port) boots to a multi-user shell on a CPC 6128 + 512 KB + SymbIface IDE, and also boots off an Albireo (CH376) USB-mass-storage image. Three port-decoding fixes landed during bring-up: FDC reads now gate on lo bit 7 = 0 so peripherals at 0xFB80+ aren't shadowed; CRTC write decode now requires A9 = 0 so spurious writes to read ports stop clobbering R12; CH376 raises INT# on host-mode SET_USB_MODE and implements DISK_INIT so FUZIX's ch375 driver completes its handshake. UI: in-window footer showing model and F-key hints; cfg.scale = 1..4 is now honoured at startup, with Ctrl ± to resize at runtime. Plus CPC 664 model support, F10 host mount of card images for drag-and-drop file exchange, M4 SymbOS networking fix, dual-CH376 Albireo with opt-in USB HID mouse, and a Windows .exe icon.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.6" date="2026-06-14">
      <description>
        <p>Closes the residual HDCPM / CP/M+ cold-reset race (#129): the Gate Array now acknowledges its 300 Hz interrupt before the Z80's interrupt-entry cycles advance the bus, matching Caprice32 / konCePCja and reaching 13/13 PASS on the canonical |hdcpm arrival-frame sweep with Net4CPC disabled. Net4CPC gains IPRAW socket mode so PING.COM works end-to-end, a brief ARP retry on miss before reporting failure, the PHYSR0 register alias / W5100S-correct default, and a full silicon-defaults reset on MR.RST. Z80 cycle accuracy: IM1=20 / IM2=28 plus a complete iWSAdjust pipeline-hint set (LDIR/LDDR, LD A,I/R, DD/FD INC/DEC and RET cc not-taken), and OUT (n),A now splits into pre-IO tick and post-IO settle so peripherals see the correct mid-instruction bus phase.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.5" date="2026-06-10">
      <description>
        <p>Renderer perf: cached resolved inks + precomputed pen tables collapse the per-pixel scalar work in render_char to a flat 16-pixel write, freeing meaningful frame headroom on slower hardware. Video capture: F6 records a GIF (in-tree encoder, no extra dependencies) and Overlay → Capture video saves WebM/VP9 via ffmpeg when available. Snapshot load/save with .sna v1-v3 support. Net4CPC gains a one-click TAP backend on Linux with built-in DHCP server, DNS proxy and NAT, plus an if_tap backend on FreeBSD / NetBSD / OpenBSD. Per-board ROM groupings: ROMs follow the M4 / Albireo / Cyboard toggle automatically. Stability: konCePCja cc_op cycle-table port fixes the HDCPM / CP/M+ kernel-ISR bank-save/restore race, plus several segfault hazards in the file-dialog callback, video capture, FDC and snapshot paths.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.4" date="2026-06-05">
      <description>
        <p>HDCPM / CP/M+ boots fully to the A0:CPM&gt; prompt from FAT-formatted SYMBiFACE II / Cyboard IDE drives, mounting up to four CPMDSKxx.IMG images. SymbOS desktop runs on both Albireo (CH376 USB) and Cyboard (Net4CPC + RTC + SYMBiFACE IDE). Two CPU/interrupt fixes underneath: the Gate Array IRQ acknowledge is now deferred until the Z80 actually accepts the maskable interrupt (so the 300 Hz IRQ cadence stays stable across IFF1-masked sections), and RETI restores IFF1 from IFF2 like Caprice32 / WinAPE / MAME.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.1" date="2026-05-30">
      <description>
        <p>Cassette tape support (.cdt/TZX) with loading screech mixed into PSG audio; fullscreen letterbox gutter colour fix.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
</component>
